[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint is the the practice of non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you... how can you go about this, like, not being... not distracting yourself all the time?
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way that... it says... the Buddha says, he's an intent on wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intent on...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not, like, holding on to your wakefulness neurotically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically intent on not losing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how you lose it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You lose it by giving in to a non-wakeful intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot accidentally lose your wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even lapsing in terms of your thoughts or something similar, it's not necessarily you lost wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You lose wakefulness when you intentionally give in to distraction or lust or anger and aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, in relation to the previous... well, one of the previous talks was to keep questioning yourself, your motivation, so that your own intentions can become transparent and clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you will know, even if sometimes people say, oh, you know, I'm engaged with, like, spreading the dhamma, but they're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their intentions are rooted in the desire for distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire for saying something to do, giving this this worldly purpose to my life, because otherwise, just boredom and anxiety sets in and it's too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that case, that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although you might be actually parroting the Buddha's words and publishing the Buddha's words, it's not the actual dhamma, which is always non-aversion, non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, non-distraction, wakefulness and knowledge.
They won't think, you know, not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like being able to just relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can relax perfectly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can actually... You would be relaxed all the time, if you can start discerning your intentions and then just... You don't have to... And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people don't discern intentions, they tend to either indulge them all or dismiss them all, because they don't see anything in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a person starts discerning their own motivation, their own intentions, then you know, actually, these intentions are not rooted in greed, nor aversion, nor delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you get relaxed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only you have to abandon those that are rooted in desire for distraction, desire for sensuality, desire for aversion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose, when you're coming from, you know, just relaxing into greed, or what you say, relaxing into delusion, that's all you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know this other way of relaxing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, the only notion of relaxation is relaxation of distraction that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's, yeah, that type of relaxation needs to be abandoned, because it's not relaxation, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can call it relaxation, but it's not peace, because you're fully controlled by it and fully dependent upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like watching a movie.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's all the sounds, sights, blasts, bang-bang.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dramatic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you're out through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not necessarily be actively pursuing the sensual, the full-on sensual pleasures, but it's still bound with the sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, which means it's still within the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's not just you have to abandon the obvious course, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You also have to abandon distraction that you've been gaining through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when I say abandon, it doesn't mean you obliterate any notion of your senses and deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just mean make sure that if you are engaging, that motivation, the intentions behind that engagement is not rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, which is basically delusion equals wanting distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-waiting.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those would contribute to non-wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, automatically, if it's not those, then it's automatically wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you don't... you're not doing the wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're developing it, basically, by preventing non-wakefulness to overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, intentionally, to give in to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you prevent that, and then you're automatically wakeful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it becomes effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, because you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a method or something to uphold constantly every second of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you get truly relaxed, truly peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes effort to give in to intentions, to do things upon them, be it central or non-central.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you, all you do is just abstain from the effort of engaging with sensuality, aversion, distraction, then your experience is automatically effortless and wakeful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, within that, well, you'll know exactly what to do, if you get to that point.